Sebastian Guerra

MAINFRAME NETWORK AND SECURITY SPECIALIST

Oshawa, ON | 416-836-5489 | <u>sebguecan@gmail.com</u>

Links: Github Linkedin

Summary

Solution-focused Mainframe Specialist with 15+ years of experience in the zOS field. Always looking for new challenges and milestones to achieve for the clients being supported. Experienced in zOS administration, network configuration, security management and network security. Designed and planned several Datacenter Migrations and Disaster Recovery sites. Lead trainer and documentation specialist for zOS System Programmer batches (JCL, ISPF, TSO, TN3270, Mainframe Networks, Mainframe Security and Mainframe Automation).

Experience

Morgan Stanley - Mainframe Network System Programmer

October 2024 - Current

- Wrote DFSORT Reports using SMF data to assess TLS version usage. Also created a database and reported on all connections using deprecated ciphers and TLS versions.
- Lead a security hardening project to remove ciphers that are deemed unusable due to poor security levels according to the company's standards.
- Successfully deployed solutions to prevent lower TLS level connections into the environment.
- Involved in the automation and modernization of the current environment. Working with Python, Git, Powershell, REXX and other programming languages to help script critical tasks.
- Responsible for maintaining the Mainframe Network Architecture devices and links. Also responsible for any Network Connectivity applications, such as TN3270, file transfers (SFTP, FTP, Connect Direct), Mails (CSSMTP, VPS, VPSX), and overall network availability and monitoring.

- Wrote ICETOOL Reports using SMF data to assess TN3270 capacity, non-TLS sessions that
 would have to be disabled, and general statistics to have a deeper look at the LPAR behavior and
 network workload.
- Created a set of JCL and REXX tools for healthchecking, and also used them to build a full inventory of the whole environment.
- Debugged common IBM Sterling Connect:Direct (NDM) and IPSec errors, providing an automated solution for the network disconnects. These implementations prevented any further issues with the file transfers.
- Created a list of Active IBM Sterling Connect:Direct (NDM) nodes and created documentation on Secure+ and Node Updates.
- Assessed the upgrade to zOS 3.1 and all required USS and Network changes needed for the
 project to be completed. All findings were successfully planned and an implementation plan was
 provided for them.
- Responsible of the Maintenance and Administration of the Mainframe zOS and Unix System Services (USS). Main contact for Mainframe Network Monitoring and Performance Analysis.
- Proficient with the use of Service Now as Change Management and Incident Management tool.

HCL Tech – Mainframe Network System Programmer

2020 - 2024

- Successfully planned and implemented 5 different Datacenter Migrations:
 - 1. Lift and Shift Datacenter Migration from one DC to another, both Disaster Recovery and Production; In charge of the Datacenter Mainframe Network setup and cross-organization connections, as well as the full implementation process for zOS and Storage supports.
 - 2. Hardware Refresh and Datacenter Migration from one DC to another, both Disaster Recovery and Production; In charge of the Datacenter Mainframe Network setup, along with Hardware cabling requirements and system availability on the migration.
 - 3. Hardware Refresh and Datacenter Switch from Disaster Recovery to PROD and vice versa; In charge or redesigning the existing Mainframe Network and LAN configuration, IP Addressing and internal incoming connections.
- Designed 4 Disaster Recovery Sites along with their Implementation Documentation; 3 of them were part of the Datacenter Migrations, and a full redesign of the Disaster Recovery Mainframe Network and LAN, allowing internal access to specific ports, along with a new Cisco ACI Fabric setup.
- Implemented AT-TLS in several clients, both with TLS 1.2 and TLS 1.3, including all the Mainframe RACF and ACF2 Certificate implementation for the applications involved (FTP, TN3270, DB2, CICS, zSecure, zOSMF, Sailpoint).
- Security and Network Security Specialist, RACF, Top Secret and ACF2; Well versed in Certificate implementations and renewals. Successfully migrated from GSKKYMAN certificate key database to both RACF and ACF2 SAF administration. Recommended several Security Hardening projects aligned with the best practices and global corporate standards (Zero Trust, Cipher Options, Keybit Size for Certificates, Proper Certificate Management, TLS Implementation, SSH Implementation, Securing Profiles in RACF and ACF2). Managed RACF, ACF2 and Top Secret environments.
- Managed and coordinated several discipline teams to complete several implementation projects, such as: Disaster Recoveries, AT-TLS migration for CICS and DB2, Certificate Renewals, SAF Migrations (GSKKYMAN to RACF and GSKKYMAN to ACF2).
- Implemented OSPF Dynamic Routing and Migrated from RIP Dynamic Routing to a Trunkmanaged link.
- Migrated FTP to SFTP for Enterprise Wide clients; The full project was designed, planned, documented and implemented from scratch.

- Performed Penetration Testing and Network Reconnaissance drills; In charge of open port discovery on one of our Enterprise Network clients, assessing points of access for malicious actors and promptly securing them. In charge of a Network and USS Penetration testing from the client side, supporting our outsource vendor, including Privilege Escalation, SSH Credential impersonation, RACF Database Copy and Userbase lookup, and Non-TLS open ports discovery.
- Troubleshooted and resolved Data Migration datacenter-wide across the globe; FTP transactions
 were dropping due to timeouts, and after intensive investigation and troubleshooting, it was assessed
 that the problem was a Firewall timeout that was promptly corrected, resulting in the project's
 successful ending.
- Generated several internal documentation regarding product maintenance and upgrades, Security Implementation, Certificate Work, Network Security, as well as leading the training of the latest batch of zOS System Programmers; In charge of remote and on-site Mainframe zOS, Network, Security, Automation, and Basic zOS knowledge training for college graduates
- Implemented SNMP in zOS, R18, VTS and DS8910 for a Solarwinds monitoring project; In charge of implementing SNMP Trap Forward for the devices required by the Solarwinds team needed to monitor.
- Created documentation and several ICETOOL reports reading SMF data; In charge of TYPE 119 SMF record sorting and formatting to provide information and further analyze the network performance of several applications (FTP, TN3270, CICS).
- Regularly supports Session Managers, File transfer programs, Printing services, and ensure Network services for all applications running on the Mainframe.
- Responsible of the Maintenance and Administration of the Mainframe zOS and Unix System Services (USS). Main contact for Mainframe Network Monitoring and Performance Analysis.
- Proficient with the use of Service Now as Change Management and Incident Management tool.

AT&T Argentina - Mainframe Network System Programmer

2009 - 2020

- Started as a Mainframe Network Operator and escalated to be Team Leader for one of the main clients in IBM Europe.
- Implemented AT-TLS on zOS 2.1 (First Implementation on IBM internal systems); Lead the AT-TLS implementation project on IBM Systems and IBM Client Systems.
- Lead a team of seasoned professionals; In charge of leading and providing training on new products and implementations for a roster of Senior Mainframe Network System Programmers.
- Migrated data across Europe for a Datacenter Migration plan for one of the clients.
- Troubleshooted, debugged and resolved SNA Transaction errors for a Major Bank in Asia; In charge of assessing an SNA LU-LU transaction error on a client, going down to reading SNA Traces, troubleshooting and debugging Windows Server SNA configuration along with Mainframe VTAM APPLID LU-LU LOGMODEs.
- Created documentation and a training curriculum for all the Mainframe Network Operators, resulting in the promotion of several of them to a higher resolution level support; A full 6-month course was created along a teammate that was also promoted to L3, teaching concepts such as VTAM, SNA, TCPIP, USS, FTP, TN3270, Network Security, Session Managers, etc.
- Generated and maintained documentation for the entire organization; Created Operations Support documentation, AT-TLS implementation, 3745 NCP Decommission, APPN Implementation.
- Part of the Operations Support team for 4 years.

Education

Skills & abilities

- zOS Specialist
- Mainframe Network SME (TCPIP and VTAM Expert)
- Mainframe Security (RACF, Top Secret, ACF2)
- Mainframe Network Security (IPSec, SSH, TLS)
- Session Managers (SuperSession, Netmaster, TPX)
- Printing Services (VPS, APF, NPF, JES Printers)
- File Transfer Protocols (SFTP, FTP, FTPS, XCOM, Connect Direct NDM, Netview FTP)
- Mainframe Network Monitoring and Performance Analysis
- Mainframe Automation
- REXX, JCL and CLIST proficient
- USS Management, Maintenance and Administration
- zOS Management, Maintenance and Administration
- Training and Documentation Lead
- Service Now Change Management and Incident Management
- HMC OSD and OSC Management
- Disaster Recovery Planning and Design
- Datacenter Migration Planning and Design
- Ethical Hacking and Penetration Testing